Welcome to this introduction to quantum computing.
Quantum computers use principles of quantum mechanics
to process information in fundamentally different ways than classical computers.
The basic unit of quantum information is called a qubit.
Unlike classical bits which can only be zero or one,
qubits can exist in a superposition of both states simultaneously.
This property allows quantum computers to perform certain calculations
exponentially faster than classical computers.
Another key principle is quantum entanglement,
where qubits become correlated in ways that have no classical equivalent.
Quantum algorithms like Shor's algorithm for factoring large numbers
and Grover's algorithm for searching databases demonstrate
the potential power of quantum computing.
However, quantum computers are extremely sensitive to noise
and environmental interference, a problem called decoherence.
Building practical quantum computers requires maintaining
extremely cold temperatures near absolute zero.
Current applications include cryptography, drug discovery,
optimization problems, and materials science.