Photosynthesis is the process by which plants convert light energy into chemical energy.
This process occurs primarily in the chloroplasts of plant cells.
Chlorophyll, the green pigment in chloroplasts, absorbs light energy.
The process can be divided into two main stages: light-dependent reactions
and light-independent reactions, also known as the Calvin cycle.
During light-dependent reactions, water molecules are split,
releasing oxygen as a byproduct and generating ATP and NADPH.
These energy carriers are then used in the Calvin cycle
to fix carbon dioxide into glucose and other organic compounds.
The overall equation for photosynthesis is:
six carbon dioxide plus six water plus light energy
yields one glucose molecule plus six oxygen molecules.
Photosynthesis is crucial for life on Earth as it produces
the oxygen we breathe and forms the base of most food chains.
Different wavelengths of light are absorbed differently by chlorophyll.
Red and blue light are absorbed most efficiently,
while green light is reflected, which is why plants appear green.
Environmental factors like light intensity, carbon dioxide concentration,
and temperature can affect the rate of photosynthesis.
Plants have evolved various adaptations to optimize photosynthesis,
such as C4 and CAM pathways for plants in hot, dry climates.